Josef Van der Kar papers M2130
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Josef Van der Kar papers
c. 1930s-2010s
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Van der Kar, Josef
Head, Jeffrey
Braseth, Tim
Malani, Lloyd
M2130
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Content Description
Materials include correspondence, photographs, articles, historic building reports, books, catalogs, and other printed material related to Josef Van der Kar's life and work.
Biographical / Historical
Josef Van der Kar (1906-2002) was a second-generation modernist architect. For ten years he taught architecture at Pennsylvania State, but prior to that he had lived in Los Angeles, and he returned to Los Angeles upon his retirement. Though most of his work was in the Los Angeles area, Van der Kar's work can also be found in New York, San Francisco, Berkeley, Santa Barbara, and more.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifted to Stanford University by Tim Braseth, Jeffrey Head and Lloyd Malani in memory of Joseph and Peter Van der Kar.
Architects; Architecture, Modern -- 20th century; Architecture -- California -- Los Angeles; Van der Kar, Josef
- Articles about Josef Van der Kar (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Rootenberg House historic site information; schematic of a house - unidentified; Schindler House - Habitat Group Los Angeles; nominations of six hisotoric structures - flyer (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Back to the future - photocopy of article about modernist houses from Los Angeles Times, September 11, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Marine gunner Joseph Van de Kar, orders to active duty, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notice of death of Catherine Ven der Kar; Notice of death of Josef Van der Kar (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Booklet reprinted for Catherine and Van's 65th Anniversary, 25 August, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Booklet reprinted for Catherine and Van's 65th Anniversary, 25 August, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Black and white photographs of Catherine and Van Van der Kar (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black and white photographs of Catherine and Van Van der Kar (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black and white photographs of Van de Kar's home [in State College?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Black and white photographs of the Van de Kar's home [in State College?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Color photographs of the Van der Kar's home (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Potpourri by Josef Vand der Kar (Box 1, Folder 8)
- LAMA December 4, 2005; Arts & Culture: spirit of LA 2007 annual report (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Unrequited self-love by Josef Van der Kar, autographed. Book number 46 of 500 numbered copies, 1982 (Box 1)
- Articles from newspapers and magazines; appraisal report of property on Old Chimney Rd. in Malibu, 2002 (Flat-box 2)
- Photographs: of the building of a house; of houses with a sign indicating it is a historic building; some miscellaneous photographs (Flat-box 2)